<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A retrayt sounded to certaine brethren lately seduced by the schismaticall Brownists to forsake the church written by Edward Iames ...</title>
            <author>James, Edward.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04324</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14435.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4715</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23817837</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23817837</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26877</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04324)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26877)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1834:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A retrayt sounded to certaine brethren lately seduced by the schismaticall Brownists to forsake the church written by Edward Iames ...</title>
                  <author>James, Edward.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Simon Stafford, dwelling in the Cloth-Fayre neere the Red Lyon,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Brownists --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26877:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26877:1"/>
            <p>A RETRAYT SOVNDED TO CER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine brethren, lately ſeduced by the Schiſmaticall Browniſts to forſake the Church.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>Edward Iames,</hi> Maſter in the Artes, and Miniſter of Gods word.</p>
            <p>Printed at London by <hi>Simon Stafford,</hi> dwelling in the Cloth-Fayre, neere the red Lyon. 1607.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26877:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26877:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A RETRAIT SOVNDED</hi> to certaine brethren, lately ſeduced by the <hi>Schiſmaticall</hi> Browniſts, <hi>to forſake</hi> the Church.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Philoſophers in old time did account it <hi>humanum errare,</hi> in matters Philoſophicall, a thing incident to man to erre: but <hi>in errore perſeuerare, belluinum,</hi> a beaſtly thing to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere in error. And Diuines may iudge it <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum,</hi> a thing incident to man, to erre in matters Theologicall: but <hi>in errore perſeuerare pernicioſum,</hi> to perſeuere in error, that in matters Theologicall muſt needs be deadly: eſpecially if a man doth ſo cleaue to error, that he chooſeth rather to forſake the Church, then to forgoe his errour: for ſeeing the Church is the mother of the faithfull, whoſoeuer doth cut himſelfe there-from, he muſt needs be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe: and therefore what goodly ſhewes ſoeuer he doth make, yet if the Apoſtles wordes be true, he cannot pleaſe God: Euery man therfore that would be acceptable vnto God, had neede to get himſelfe into the boſome of the Church, and being once got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten thither, not to ſuffer himſelfe in any wiſe, to be remoued there-from. For as none could be deliuered from the deluge, but ſuch as were contained in <hi>Noabs</hi> Arke: ſo can none be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from eternall death, but onely thoſe who keepe themſelues within the Church of God. Theſe are common principles, which no man that accounts himſelfe a Chriſtian, can or will deny.</p>
            <p>But the controuerſie which doth trouble ſeduced braines, is of the Church it ſelfe: what it is, &amp; where it ſhould be ſought for. Papiſts would tye the Church to Rome: ſo that if we credit them,
<pb facs="tcp:26877:3"/>then muſt we confeſſe, that as many as made a ſeparation from the Romane Biſhop, haue likewiſe made a ſeparation from the Church of God. And all other Sectaries doe tye the Church vnto their ſects: whereas it were farre fitter for euery man to tye him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnto the Church: which that we may with eaſe performe, it is very fit and meete, firſt, to define the vniuerſall Church, that we may know what it is: ſecondly, to expreſſe and lay downe the true notes and markes, whereby true particular Churches (which are very members of that vniuerſall Church) may be knowne from other congregations: which when we haue once found out, then may we cleaue vnto the Church with great ſecurity.</p>
            <p>The word <hi>Eccleſia,</hi> in Engliſh, Church, is a Greeke word, &amp; doth properly ſignifie a congregation: and yet euery congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not the Church of God; but that congregation onely, which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> doth tearme<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>er.</hi> 12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12.</note> 
               <hi>Christs body,</hi> of the which Chriſt himſelfe is head. And as the ſoule of man giueth life vnto mans body: ſo Chriſts ſpirit giueth life vnto this body of Chriſt; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto Chriſts words:<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ohn</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>It is the ſpirit which giueth life,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Neither is there any thing which doth maintaine, and ioyne in one, the members of this body, beſides this ſpirit, according vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that of <hi>Paul, For by one ſpirit,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>are we all baptized into one body, whether we be lewes, or Grecians, bond, or free, &amp;c.</hi> Euen as therefore a dead body, whoſe ſoule is already departed, can receiue neither fruite, nor comfort from any meate, or drinke: ſo that congregation, which is deſtitute of Gods ſpirit, can receiue from Gods word, which is the true ſpirituall meate, neither fruite nor comfort: and therefore it is, that the Apoſtle telleth vs: <hi>Though</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>er.</hi> 6.</note> Paul <hi>plans, and</hi> Apollo <hi>water, yet that it is God which doth giue the encreaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As therefore it is euident, that euery member of mans body is liuely, wherein the ſoule remaineth: ſo euery congregation, in the which Gods ſpirit worketh, muſt needs be a true and liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly member of Chriſts body: ſo that God is tyed to no one part of the world, more then vnto another, becauſe he is God of all the world: euen ſo the Church of God is tyed to no part of the world, becauſe it containeth in it, all the beleeuers, who are ſeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered ouer all the world.</p>
            <p>This Church being one, yet may it be conſidered diuerſly:
<pb facs="tcp:26877:3"/>either as it is hidden from, and inuiſible vnto men, and knowne onely vnto him, from whom nothing can be hidden: or as it is viſible, conſpicuous, and apparant vnto men: as it is inuiſible, and hidden from the ſight of men, it containeth onely thoſe, who appertaine vnto Gods free election, and ſhall moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be ſaued. And the reaſon why in this reſpect the Church is ſaid to be hidden from men, is, becauſe God onely knoweth who are his: neither can man know them, whileſt he liueth here vpon the earth: but the Church, as it is viſible, apparant, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous vnto men, doth containe all thoſe, who in their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward behauiour worſhip one God, embrace one Chriſt, profeſſe one Goſpell, hearken vnto one word, and vſe the ſame Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: many of theſe may be rauening wolues, and wicked re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates, and yet they may be ſo cloſe in cariage, and their ſinnes may be ſo ſecret, that the Church cannot diſcerne them, and therefore cannot diſcarde them, vntill God doth make them manifeſt. Hence it is, that the Church thus conſidered, is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by our Sauiour Chriſt vnto a<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. <hi>ver.</hi> 12.</note> threſhing floore, where the wheate and chaffe are ſo mixed together, that they cannot be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, before he with his fanne doth ſeuer them: vnto a<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13 <hi>ver.</hi> 15.</note> field, where doe grow both corne and weedes together, which cannot be ſeperated before the harueſt: vnto a<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 47.</note> net, in the which fiſh both good and bad are contained, which cannot be ſundred, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till both be brought vnto the ſhore. And as this is the eſtate of the generall and vniuerſall Church, militant here in earth, ſo is it the eſtate of euery branch, or member thereof, I meane, of euery particular Church or congregation: whether it be contained within one Realme, Prouince, or Dioceſſe, or doe conſiſt of thouſands, hundreds, more or fewer, it hath euer ſome lewd and wicked men amongſt the good and godly Saints of God. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth theſe mens wickedneſſe make it to ceaſe to be a Church, although they are ſuffred to liue within it. Would you haue it proued by examples, it may be done with eaſe: I will let paſſe the auncient Iewiſh Church, and come vnto Chriſt his time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> writeth vnto the Galathians, as vnto the<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gala.</hi> 1 <hi>ver.</hi> 2.</note> Church of God: and yet he ſaith, that they are<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 6</note> remoued vnto another Goſpell: that they were<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. <hi>ver.</hi> 1.</note> fooliſh, bewitched, and diſobedient
<pb facs="tcp:26877:4"/>vnto the truth. Lo then, behold men fooliſh, men bewitched, men diſobedient vnto the truth, and remoued to another Goſpell, and yet a Church. Amongſt the Corinthians there were ſects, enuie, ſtrife, diſcenſion, and ſuch inceſt, as was not once named amongſt the Gentiles: they abuſed the Lords ſupper, and many of them denied the reſurrection of the dead; and yet <hi>Paul</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vnto this by the name of the<note n="(d)" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. <hi>Verſe.</hi> 2.</note> Church of God which was at Corinth. Nay, caſt your eyes vpon Chriſts owne Diſciples, and there you ſhall finde a Iudas: and yet his wickednes was not ſo forcible, but that Chriſts Diſciples were ſtill a Church.</p>
            <p>So then it followeth, that there may be in a congregation, not onely wicked men, but euen wicked Miniſters; and yet that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation may be a true part, or parcell, of that generall, catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke, and vniuerſall Church, which comprehendeth all Gods choſen: ſo that although that, which Chriſt ſaith, that by their fruites, men ſhall know true, from falſe ſeducing Prophets, be very true, and certaine, (for that thoſe who preach the truth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainedly, ſetting only Gods glory, and the ſaluation of their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns ſoules before their eyes, are only to be tearmed true Prophets, and theſe do euer liue vprightly, as farre forth as fleſh and bloud will ſuffer them) yet notwithſtanding it followeth not, but that amongſt theſe faithfull and vnfained Paſtors, there may be other, who teach for a time the truth, and yet be deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full workmen, and rauening wolues, who doe but watch fit op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to prey vpon Gods people, as <hi>Iudas</hi> watched his op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie to betray Chriſt Ieſus. Of this ſort, were thoſe, of whom Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh<note n="(e)" place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>ver.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>They went from vs, but they were not of vs, &amp;c.</hi> Such be the cloſe Atheiſts, and Neuters of the world, which liue in euery age, and almoſt in euery congregation, who haue two faces vnder one hood with <hi>Ianus,</hi> and with the Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leon can turne themſelues vnto any colour: ſuch doe liue and teach in many faithfull congregations, and hardly can they be certainely diſcerned from faithfull Paſtors, vntill the time of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution: for that is like Chriſt his fanne, wherewith he ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the wheate from chaffe; the wheate remaineth, the chaffe is carried with that wind, from the threſhing floore, which is Chriſt his Church: for whileſt the Church enioyeth peace and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, it is gouerned with diſcipline, and ruled with lawes, and
<pb facs="tcp:26877:4"/>Canons, whereof ſome prohibite the broaching of vntrue doctrine, and not onely admit into no dignities, but withall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh ſuch as broach it. Others correct the maners, and beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour of lewde liuers, profane perſons, and all their wicked actions: and therefore feare, and ambition, doe make thoſe hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritiſh cormorants, to teach but truth; &amp; at leaſtwiſe to ſeeme to liue within their liſts: but when the Churches peace is turned into perſecution, when, for executing lawes, it be driuen to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer violence, and that all dignities and preferments are taken from it: then, though their ambition ſtill remaineth, yet their hope of preferments by the Church, is quite cut off: and though then they feare ſuch tyrants, as vſurpe authoritie; yet the feare they had to offend the Churches lawes, is departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them: and therefore then, and not before, they ſhew what they were before: they embrue their hands in the Churches deareſt bloud, who lately ſeemed to be their deareſt mother: and they endeuour to wound her to death, who would haue nouriſhed them to euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life. It is not to be doubted, as wily as theſe Foxes are, but that in the time, that the Church doth flouriſh, they doe often commit ſuch wickednes, as is not to be once named: yet for that their actions are ſometimes ſo ſecret, that they come not to the knowledge of thoſe, in whoſe hands it is to cut men off from Gods aſſemblies: and ſometimes, when they are conuented for their enormities, they ſayne ſuch penitencie, that for the hope men haue of their amendments, they are ſuffred to liue within the Church: and ſometimes, as well through the negligence of thoſe who ſhould informe the gouernors, as of the gouernors them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, many of their iniquities are winked at, and they are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer called into queſtion for them:</p>
            <p>I conclude therefore, that the lewd maners of men, liuing in any congregation, is no certaine note, whereby that congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation may be iudged to be no Church: eſpecially, if the notes whereby a Church may be diſcerned, be to be found therein: and theſe notes are two: Truth of doctrine, and the right vſe of the ſacred Sacraments. This truth muſt be grounded vpon Gods word; and theſe Sacraments muſt be the very ſame, which Chriſt did inſtitute to be moſt certaine ſeales of our deliuerie, and moſt vndoubted pledges of our Vnion with Chriſt Ieſus,
<pb facs="tcp:26877:5"/>Where the former is truely taught, and the later rightly mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, it cannot be, but that that aſſembly is aſſembled in Chriſt his name: and therefore it cannot be, but that there Chriſt is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: and vndoubtedly, that aſſembly where Chriſt is preſent, muſt needs be Chriſt his Church.</p>
            <p>Againe, this word of God, whereſoeuer it be truely taught, doth worke effectually, in ſome vnto ſaluation, and in ſome vnto the contrarie: and who knoweth not, but that where the ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of men is wrought, there is a Church, ſeeing that out of the Church there is no ſaluation: But ſeeing that vnto others it works perdition, in the ſame aſſembly; vnto whom as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, <hi>It is a ſauour of death, vnto death,</hi> (though it be ſaid before, that truth of doctrine, and right vſe of Sacraments, be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted notes of Chriſt his Church) yet hereby we may perceine, that, that is not to be ſo ſtrictly vnderſtood, but that in the Church, there may happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in doctrine ſome error, &amp; in the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Sacraments ſome abuſes: for that it is impoſſible, that Gods enemies, whoſe hearts are hardned in the hearing of Gods word, ſhould be altogether faithfull teachers, or obedient hearers. And hence it is, that in the Galathian Church, men were bewitched, &amp; turned fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the truth of Gods word, vnto ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Goſpell: &amp; hence it is, that ſome in the Corinthian Church<note n="(a)" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note> denied the reſurrection of the dead: and others<note n="(b)" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Lords Supper, moſt pernitiouſly: and yet there ceaſed not to be a Church, in the one or other of them. So that in a true Church, there may be in doctrine error, and in Sacraments abuſes: a true Church, I ſay, as long as it doth but ſuffer, and not maintaine theſe errors, and abuſes: and therefore whoſoeuer doth ſeparate himſelfe from ſuch a Church, he ſeparateth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from the true Arke, from the holy congregation, and from Gods fauour, neither can he be ſaued, vnleſſe he doth returne againe into the ſame. Nay, there may be in doctrine errours, and in Sacraments abuſes, ſo tolerable, that though the Church doth teach and maintaine them openly: yet as long as they are not in matters neceſſarie vnto ſaluation, it is intolerable for a man for theſe errours and abuſes, to cut himſelfe off from the Church. Such are the errours which may happen, concerning things, not as yet fully reuealed vnto men; As for example: One congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation
<pb facs="tcp:26877:5"/>may teach, that hell is in the center of the earth: ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that it is vpon the earth: a third, that it ſtandeth in the ayre: a fourth, that it is compaſſed with fire, that higheſt element: and all theſe congregations may teach theſe oppoſit doctrines pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely: and yet all of them may be Churches, and true parts and parcels of the Catholike and Vniuerſall Church.</p>
            <p>The like may be ſaid of the ſoules of Saints departed: One congregation may maintaine, that they be already in their full and perfect bliſſe: another may be perſwaded, that they haue not as yet receiued the fulneſſe of their ioy: and a third may thinke it a point of raſhneſſe, to define with the one, or with the other: and yet all three may be Gods aſſemblies: yea, in diſtant Churches there may be diuerſe and diſagreeing ceremonies in the adminiſtration of Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper: yet as long as theſe are not contentiouſly maintained, or enioyned to be obſerued, as things neceſſary vnto ſaluation, God forbid, that any Chriſtian ſhould for theſe, ſeuer himſelfe from any of them.</p>
            <p>Seeing then, my deare friends, theſe things be thus: and that you haue ſeuered your ſelues from our aſſemblies, it ſtandeth you vpon, to ſhew in doctrine ſome grieuous and pernicious errors, and in the miniſtration of the Sacraments, ſome dangerous and damnable abuſes, which are maintained, and publikely defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by vs: or at leaſt, ſome ſmall errours or abuſes, contentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defended, and violently thruſt vpon men, to be by them firme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleeued, and receiued as things neceſſary vnto ſaluation: (which you cannot doe) or elſe you muſt acknowledge, that your eſtate is dangerous, as indeede it is: as muſt needs be the eſtate of them, that haue wilfully made a ſeparation from that body, whereof Chriſt is head: out of the which there is no ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: which if once you could be induced to beleeue, I doubt not, but you would with as great alacritie ioyne your ſelues vnto vs, as euer you went out from vs: for I know full well, that zeale hath made this ſeparation, but it was not a zeale grounded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on knowledge: and therefore, if now you would receiue true inſtructions, and to ioyne knowledge vnto your zeale: then that very zeale, which vnaduiſedly did thruſt you out, would now, being guided with vnderſtanding, bring you backe againe, vnto
<pb facs="tcp:26877:6"/>the boſome of Chriſt his body myſticall; which may be a ioy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men and Angels, and a comfort vnto your very ſoules: out of the which, as long as obſtinately you ſtand, (pardon me, truth is truth, and muſt be plainely told) you cannot but vainely hope for the ſaluation of your ſoules: it doth as much greeue me to vtter it, as it greeueth any of you to heare it: you may through your conuerſions, conuert, and turne theſe grieues to ioy.</p>
            <p>If you will ſtand in your owne defence, and tell me, that you liue within the boſome of that Catholike and vniuerſall Church, whereof Chriſt is head, although you will not communicate with the members of the Church of England; I muſt tell you, that this defence doth mightily offend the Church of God, God himſelfe, and you very ſoules; for that the coniunction is ſo neere, betweene the Catholike Church, and all the parts, &amp; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels thereof, (I meane particular Churches) that whoſoeuer doth ſeuer himſelfe from any of theſe branches, he is become thereby no branch of Chriſt his Church.</p>
            <p>If you ſay, that our Engliſh Church is no Church at all, and ſo no part of Chriſt his Church: and therefore that you may, and muſt ſeuer your ſelfe there-from: it is ſoone ſaid, but hardly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, my good brethren: neither can you euer proue it, vntill you proue, that this Church maintaineth ſome pernicious do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which ouerthroweth the foundation of the faith: or that it doth ſo wickedly abuſe the Sacraments, or either of them, that their force and efficacie is altogether weakened, and become of no validitie. If theſe things could be proued, then might you (peraduenture) iuſtifie your doings: but if all the world would ioyne in one, and bend themſelues againſt vs, I know, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſpeake it, theſe things could not be proued, no not by all the world.</p>
            <p>Be you not therefore obſtinate, neither hinder you your own ſaluation: nor yet obiect that, which by men of your ſect is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly obiected; That the whole face of our Church is ſo ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with vices, that in outward ſhew, it ſeemeth rather to be the Synagogue of Sathan, then the Church of God; &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that it is impietie, in any Chriſtian, to ioyne himſelfe vnto it. Surely I muſt needs confeſſe vnto you, that our liues are not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable vnto our calling, &amp; that from the higheſt to the loweſt,
<pb facs="tcp:26877:6"/>we haue in many things offended: yet I would haue you to confeſſe,<note n="(a)" place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24. <hi>Matt.</hi> 16. <hi>v</hi> 22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 26. <hi>ver.</hi> 70, 72 74.</note> that the very worthieſt members of Chriſtes Church, haue often moſt grieuouſly offended: and therefore, that in our Church, there may be many, euen great offenders, who are true members of Chriſt his body: neither ſhould you doubt, but that of thoſe, whom the contagion of ſinne hath mightily infected, there are very many, who are grieued with the burthen of their iniquities, and being ſtrooke with true remorſe of conſcience, aſpire vnto innocencie of life and conuerſation.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe indeed, that, that generall iniquitie, which coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, in a maner, the whole earth, hath often grieued me, and troubled my conſcience greatly, and had almoſt thruſt me raſbly into thoſe mens company, with whoſe company alone you ſeeme to be delighted: but I thanke my God, he opened the eyes of mine vnderſtanding, and I did in good time per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, that there is greater efficacie, in Gods word truely taught, and his Sacramentes rightly adminiſtred, to beget children vnto God, then can be diſanulled, by the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of rebellious and diſobedient children: and therefore farre be it from me, from euer ſeuering of my ſelfe from that company, wherein this word is truely taught, and theſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments rightly adminiſtred, as in our aſſemblies I know they are. Our ſinnes are great indeede, and our iniquities are many in number: yet compare our Church, with the olde aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of the Iſraelites, before Chriſts birth, and you ſhall finde, that we are not gone beyond them; nay, as whicked as we are, if you vouchſafe to read Gods booke with a ſingle eye, you ſhall find aſſuredly, that they had gone beyond vs in iniquities: Their Princes are called by the name of the<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 1 <hi>verſe</hi> 9.</note> Princes of <hi>Sodome:</hi> and the people are called the people of <hi>Gomorha.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How ſaith he, is<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 21 23.</note> the faithfull Citie, become an har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot? it was full of iudgement, and iuſtice lodged therein: but now they are murtherers; thy ſiluer is become droſſe, thy wine is mixed with water, thy Princes are rebellious, and companions of theeues: euery one loueth gifts, &amp; followeth after rewards; they
<pb facs="tcp:26877:7"/>iudge not the fatherleſſe, neither doth the widdowes cauſe come before them: the Prieſts and Prophets of Ephraim, are ſaid to<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 28 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.7, 8.</note> haue erred through ſtrong drinke, &amp;c. to haue fayled in viſion, and to haue ſtumbled in iudgement: all, ſaith he, their tables are full of filthy vomiting, and there is no place cleane a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them:<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 29 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.10, 13.</note> the eyes of the Seers and Prophets are ſhut vp with a ſpirit of ſlumber, ſo that they cannot ſee, and the people are ſaid to come neere him with their lips, and to haue remoued their hearts farre from him:<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 56 <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>trſ.</hi> 10.</note> their watchmen are ſaid to be all blind, to haue no knowledge, to be dumme dogges, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not barke, to be ſuch as lye and ſleepe, and delight in ſleeping.</p>
            <p>How ſay you, my brethren, are our Princes like the Princes of <hi>Sodome?</hi> are they rebellious and companions of theeues? doe all of them loue gifts, and follow after rewards? iudge they not the fatherleſſe, &amp; commeth not the widowes cauſe before them? what? haue our Prieſts &amp; Prophets erred, through ſtrong drink? haue they fayled in viſion, and ſtumbled in their iudgements? are their eyes couered and ſhut vp with a ſpirit of ſlumber? are our watchmen blind? haue they no knowledge? be they dumbe dogs which cannot barke? are they ſuch as lye and ſleepe, &amp; delight in ſleeping? are our people like the people of <hi>Gomorha?</hi> are our aſſemblies become harlots, and our congregations theeues? is our ſiluer become droſſe, and our wine mixed with water? are our tables full of filthy vomiting? and are all places amongſt vs vncleane? doe our people with their lips, come neere vnto the Lord, and are their hearts far from him? Surely it were very hard, to giue ſo hard a cenſure, againſt all our Magiſtrates, all our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and all our people.</p>
            <p>Yet admit, that our Magiſtrates, Miniſters, and people, were ſuch as I haue heere deſcribed, were it fit, that therfore we ſhould make a ſeperation from them, hauing his word truely taught, and his Sacraments rightly adminiſtred amongſt them? Surely no (my beloued brethren) for I haue already proued, that in the time of <hi>Eſay,</hi> ſuch were the Magiſtrates, Miniſters, and people of <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> and yet <hi>Eſay,</hi> though he ſharply reproued them for their iniquities, yet did he not ſeuer himſelfe from their aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, nor erect another Church, other Altars, other ſacrifices, or other ceremonies: but in the middeſt of a peruerſe and fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb facs="tcp:26877:7"/>generation, he lifted vp pure hands vnto the Lord.</p>
            <p>Neither was that ancient Church thus generally corrupted, in the time of <hi>Eſay</hi> onely: peruſe the other Prophets, &amp; you ſhall finde the very ſame, or the like deſcriptions, in their volumes: it were in a maner infinit, to lay down all their words;<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 22. <hi>and</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 1.7, 8, 26. <hi>&amp;</hi> 28. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7, <hi>v.</hi> 11.17, 18, 19, 30, 31. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8, <hi>v.</hi> 5.6, 7, 8, 9, <hi>&amp;</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 4.5, 6, 7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11, <hi>verſ.</hi> 9, 10.13, <hi>and</hi> 19. <hi>verſ.</hi> 4, 5. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 4, 5, 6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8, <hi>from v.</hi> 5. <hi>to the end. and</hi> 14. <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>and</hi> 16. <hi>from v.</hi> 15. <hi>vnto</hi> 36. <hi>and from</hi> 45 <hi>vnto</hi> 57. <hi>and</hi> 22, <hi>through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out. Hoſ.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. <hi>and</hi> 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1, 2, 11.12, 13, <hi>and</hi> 7, <hi>tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughout. and</hi> 8, <hi>v.</hi> 11, 7, <hi>&amp;</hi> 13, <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2, <hi>and</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6, <hi>v.</hi> 3, 4, 5, 6, <hi>and</hi> 8. <hi>v.</hi> 4, 5, 6. <hi>Micah.</hi> 1, <hi>v.</hi> 5, <hi>and</hi> 2, <hi>v.</hi> 8, <hi>&amp;</hi> 3, <hi>v.</hi> 2.3, <hi>and</hi> 7, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 2, 3, 4. <hi>Mal.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 8, 12, 13, <hi>and</hi> 2, <hi>verſ.</hi> 7, 8, 11.</note> view the places quoted in the margent, and you ſhall finde what I ſay, moſt certaine &amp; vndoubted: and yet ſhew me amongſt all theſe godly Prophets, any one, which did euer ſeuer himſelfe from the Church wherein he liued: or name any of them, that did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to communicate with the wicked of their time, in the word, ſacrifices, or ceremonies, which the Lord had appointed them to vſe. Aſſuredly you cannot name me one. How then? what, are we wiſer then they were? or doe we exceede them in holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? I would to God wee were indued with the tenth part of their wiſedome, or of their holineſſe.</p>
            <p>How is it then, that any of vs ſhould be ſo preſumptuous, as to ſeuer himſelfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe congregations, which moſt aſſuredly are not ſo wicked, as thoſe aſſemblies were, with the which they were contented to aſſemble themſelues and to communicate? Doubtleſſe, had they beene perſwaded, that thoſe mens wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, with whom they did communicate, muſt of neceſſitie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect their integritie, they would haue ſuffered a thouſand deaths, rather then to haue reſorted with ſuch vnto the Synagogues.</p>
            <p>Doth the example of theſe men nothing moue you? Open then your eyes, and looke vpon <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt, looke vpon Chriſts Diſciples, and vpon Chriſt himſelfe. <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt tearmeth the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Matth. <hi>3.</hi> v. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> Scribes and Phariſees, generations of vipers: and yet<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 8, 9, 10.</note> he preacheth the word vnto them.<note n="(d)" place="margin">Matth. <hi>10.</hi> v. <hi>6.</hi> Luk. <hi>10.</hi> v. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> Chriſt his Diſciples preached among wolues: and although the Scribes and Phariſees were moſt wicked men, yet Chriſt exhorteth not his Diſciples to make a ſeperation from them: but he rather willed them to doe that which they commaunded: adding this reaſon; For that they ſit in <hi>Moſes</hi> his chayre: which is as much by the interpretation of the learned, as if he ſhould haue ſaid, For they teach the law of God, which was deliuered by the hands of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26877:8"/>
            <p>I beſeech you, tell me (my louing brethren) was it an offence, in a man regenerated, amongſt that viperous broode, to heare <hi>Iohns</hi> preaching? Or was it a thing to be reprooued in Gods choſen, to harken vnto Chriſts diſciples, in the company of thoſe wolues, vnto whom they preached? Or thinke you, that we ſhall be rebuked, for hearing of Gods word, from the mouthes of thoſe, whom we know to be wicked men, ſeeing Chriſts diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples are by Chriſt himſelfe enioyned to yeelde obedience vnto ſuch precepts, as the wicked Scribes and Phariſees gaue them? If you doubt, whether in Chriſt his time, the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, Doctors of the law, and people of the Iewes, were as wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked as this generation is; note<note n="(e)" place="margin">Iohn <hi>8.</hi> ver. <hi>13, 40, 59.</hi> and <hi>6.</hi> verſe. <hi>26, 41.</hi> Luk. <hi>23.</hi> verſ. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> but their behauiour towards Chriſt,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Mat. <hi>3.</hi> v. <hi>22.</hi> &amp; <hi>9.</hi> v. <hi>34.</hi> &amp; <hi>12</hi> verſe <hi>47.</hi>
               </note> their blaſphemie againſt him,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Luk <hi>11.</hi> from verſe <hi>42.</hi> vnto <hi>53</hi> Matt. <hi>20.</hi> v. <hi>46.</hi> Mar. <hi>12</hi> from v. <hi>38.</hi> vnto <hi>44.</hi> Iohn. <hi>8.</hi> v. <hi>2.</hi> Luk. <hi>2.</hi> v. <hi>46</hi> Mar. <hi>6.</hi> v. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> and his iudgement of them: and doubtleſſe you will confeſſe, that if they were not our ſuperiors, yet that they were our equals in iniquitie: and yet Chriſt himſelfe was contented, in theſe mens aſſemblies to preach, and to heare Gods word.</p>
            <p>How ſay you (my brethren) is not Chriſt his life a fit rule for vs to ſquare our actions by? If it be, why ſhould then the fall of thoſe, who are preſent in any aſſembly, deterre vs from preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or from hearing Gods word, in that aſſembly, ſeeing the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſally, (as I may tearme it) ouerflowing iniquitie of that age, could not hinder Chriſt, from hearing, and preaching the word amongſt them?</p>
            <p>I could here adde the generall wickedneſſe of the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians and Galathians, which I touched already: whom though Saint <hi>Paul</hi> doth earneſtly reprooue, yet notwithſtanding, he exhorteth none to ſeuer himſelfe from their ſocieties. Yea, but you doubt, leſt that your communicating with vs, ſhould argue, that you allow our wickedneſſe, and aſſent vnto our ceremonies: for I remember once, one of you told me ſome ſuch thing. But ſurely you deceiue your ſelues: for were our ceremonies abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable, as indeede they are not, and our ſinnes manifold, as indeed they are: yet conſidering what hath been already proued, you ſhould confeſſe, that the Iewes vſed as wicked ceremonies as we doe; and were as lewd in their behauiour as we are: and yet it hath beene already proued vnto you, that the auncient Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt, Chriſts Diſciples, &amp; Chriſt himſelfe, feared
<pb facs="tcp:26877:8"/>no ſuch matter; they doubted not, that communicating with theſe men, ſhould argue, that they did allow their wickedneſſe, or aſſent vnto their ceremonies. And here another obiection, vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally framed by men of that ſect you follow, falleth to the ground: The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> (ſay they) doth ſtraightly warne vs, that if<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>5.</hi> ver. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> there be one called a brother, that is a fornicator, or couetous, or an Idolater, or a rayler, or a drunkard, or an extortioner, that with ſuch we ſhould not eate. I ſay, this reaſon falleth to the ground, for that the premiſſes conſidered, it clearely appeareth, that onely priuate accompanying, and aſſociation, and not publike communicating, is here prohibited: for that otherwiſe, the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Prophets, <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt, Chriſt his Diſciples, and Chriſt himſelfe, had offended againſt this precept: which to affirme, can be no leſſe then blaſphemie.</p>
            <p>And ſurely, euery Chriſtian may be a Iudge vnto himſelfe, to diſcerne, and iudge, who are fit, and who are vnfitte for him priuately, to frequent their company: but who are fit, or vnfit with him, in publike aſſemblies, to heare Gods word, and to be partakers of his bleſſed Sacraments, this priuate men muſt not wade vnto: it muſt be left vnto the iudgement of the Church: and therefore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the ſame Epiſtle, directing vs, how to come vnto the Lords Table, doth not commaund vs, to prye one into anothers actions, or to make ſearch, whether there be wicked men amongſt vs: but hee willeth vs to<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>11.</hi> ver. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> examine our owne ſelues, and ſo without any further circumſtances, he permitteth vs to eate of that bread, and to drinke of that cup. The like he hath in the ſecond vnto the Corinths<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Cor. <hi>13.</hi> ver. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> Proue, ſaith he: whom? your ſelues, whether you are in the faith: exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine: whom? one another, no: examine your ſelues; know you not your owne ſelues, that Ieſus Chriſt is in you: except, what? your fellow-communicants? no: but except your ſelues be reprobates.</p>
            <p>For the loue of God peruſe theſe places, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider them, &amp; thinke vpon them; follow S. <hi>Pauls</hi> directions, and aſſure your ſelues, that though al were reprobates, beſides your ſelues which are in place, where you heare Gods word, or receiue his Sacraments: yet that Chriſt ſhall dwell in you, vnleſſe your ſelues be reprobates. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſinne, &amp; ſpare not, both in your ſelues, &amp; in others alſo, yea,
<pb facs="tcp:26877:9"/>deteſt it with a perfect deteſtation; yet let not this deteſtation cut you off from the Church of God: but euen as you tender Gods glory, your owne ſaluation, and ſoules health, and as you deſire to be made the member of Gods triumphant Church in Heauen, vnite and ioyne your ſelues vnto his militant Church in earth. So God ſhall take pleaſure in your doings, your ſoules ſhall be ſaued from deſtruction, and on the laſt dreadfull day, yee ſhall ſtand ſecurely before Gods throne, and ſhall heare that more then ſweete ſounding voice, <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, receiue that kingdome, which was prepared for you, before the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world.</hi> The which voyce, God of his infinit, and euer-abounding mercies graunt, that both you, and I, and all faithfull Chriſtians may heare, vnto our exceeding comfort, for his ſonne Chriſt Ieſus ſake, Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>One which thirſteth for the ſaluation of your ſoules,</hi> EDWARD IAMES.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:26877:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
